all right welcome to meditating with
John robic I'm a cognitive psychologist
and a cognitive scientist at the
University of Toronto scientifically and
academically study things like
mindfulness related phenomena like
insight Oh mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness and the cultivation of
wisdom I've also been practicing the
past and meditation met a contemplation
Tai Chi Chuan and Chacon for over 29
years and I've been teaching them
professionally for close to 20 years so
welcome this is an ongoing course what
that means is every Monday is a Dharma
day in which I teach and I explain an
important principle that builds on
previous principles and we usually do it
then we sit together and then there's a
Q&A Tuesday through Friday we meet we
sit sometimes do some review and then
there's a Q&A usually a longer Q&A at
the end of the six lessons if you're
joining us for the first time welcome to
stay but if you look in the notes for
this video
you'll find links to the previous
lessons and the previous it's divided up
into playlists so please go there if you
wish to catch up on what even this so
far so just wanted to remind everybody
that it's we don't meet anymore on
Saturdays Saturdays and Sundays you need
to continue practicing on your own you
might want to you know think about
reviewing some of the earlier lessons on
time and perhaps coming up with some
questions over the weekend from that
review that you could direct to need
when we come back together so let's
prepare to sit please please make sure
that your phone is turned off it ought
to put on do not disturb your timer is
set and ready to go and that you've got
a comfortable position adjust your make
your final adjustments into your posture
and remember that we're all sitting
together we have our virtual assignment
and let's remember that as we said okay
well begin what I say begin begin
you
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition coming out
of your sit is part of the practice so
we have some time for a couple questions
here on from our health it's good to see
you and mark is there an alternative set
of familiar questions for meta these
specific types of people are problematic
for me it's hard to know how to answer
that question mark without knowing a
little bit more about in what way
they're problematic
they're problematic because they're
bringing up all kinds of sort of
powerful emotions and associations
working with maybe just one of those in
meta until that starts to on its own
dissipate a bit and you can start to get
back from being locked into a particular
emotional frame with them might be what
you want to pursue if it's problematic
for reasons perhaps of trauma or other
things that I don't want to pry into
then you might want to just do Metta try
doing Metta towards yourself initially
and then just try doing Metta towards
all beings first of all people and then
perhaps all living beings may be a
reorientation into a more primordial on
stance with what help again it's hard to
give you specific things as I'm not
quite clear on how these people are
problematic to you so those are two
things so both of my speculations might
be incorrect and I apologize if that's
the case but if there's the deep
emotional issue then find one person I
just do met it with them stay with them
and realized that what you're trying to
do as much as possible is let that
powder a noose in a bit so you can start
to unlock from the particular emotional
situation member
is not this is not you trying to become
contrite or forgive this is just trying
to unlock unlock a pattern that you
might be locked into if it's more that
there's issues here sort of perhaps from
trauma or other things like that and
therefore it's not the right time to do
this I get that like I said maybe just
towards all people and then towards all
living beings start with yourself than
all people
so skip specific people for now but you
still try to get that expansive openness
and that trying to unlock the move the
reciprocal morna's now from Philip 86
myt this is the 100th question so thank
you Philip this is the 100th question
already we're already at 100 questions
it's it's amazing keep it up guys keep
up these great questions routing is a
new technique and becomes intensely
distracted just at the back channel
consistently why is there a location
specific trigger for the default mode
network leading to storytelling so those
of you who don't know Philip is invoking
a very prevalent theory glute Theory
from a neuroscience that we have to two
kinds of attentional networks we have a
task focused network as I mentioned
which is what we use when we're trying
to concentrate on a task and then we
have to default in the mode Network when
we look inside and that tends to get us
into mental time travel and mind
watering and what we're trying to do
actually in meditation is Co activate
because they're usually one is odd and
shutting the other off because that chol
activation is actually the most
conducive for transformative insight so
it sounds like for Philip when he's
doing the back route he's getting
triggered so there's a practical
question here I recommend that if that's
the case Philip see if you can go just
maybe just do the center route just
instead of doing front and then Center
with leaving the back just do the center
with a sense that it's sort of reaching
gently into the front of the back and
just go through the center route why
particular areas trigger the default
mode Network I don't know I mean I I
don't think of what you're finding
generalizes it
my videos in product to you that's not
saying anything
prejudicial against you by the way if so
Michael Washburn talks about the idea of
body armor that there's certain areas in
our body that we lock down and try to
control sensation of the stimulation
there because they are associated with
particular experiences that we don't
want to remember or recall or particular
emotional states or idea or states of
identity that we don't like to be in and
perhaps that's what's going on that
could be one reason why specific areas
of body trigger the default mode Network
there is there a trigger that machinery
of who am i what am I sort of playing
around with it so that's my that again I
don't know I guys that's that's please
take that for what it is it's a
speculation based on what I do know
about ideas about body armor and the
functionality of the default mode
Network MacCready any tips for centering
your attitude on days when you're
frustrated stressed or anxious yes
so such as the the order I gave you is
that's that's not just a Celsius
happenstance that's an effective order
so spend a lot so right spend a lot of
time centering the body like do it
really deeply really slowly really
extended a really center of the body and
spend a lot of time and don't worry
about sitting just really Santorini
retention really centering your
attention and then really really you
know how have you savor your postural
Center when you centered your attention
as much as you can right really savor
what's it like to be centered in my
attention and my body and then try to
carry that into centering your attitude
so you're neither fighting nor feeding
so that progression is actually
progressive it is to help you get the
centering of the thing that's actually
the most difficult to center in in many
ways which is your attitude and really
air since I'm only focusing on following
the breath labeling distractions and
trying to get familiar
with how that feels I've noticed
something I would only describe as
dopamine rushes it's not okay yes it's
it's okay you'll get dopamine rushes
what if I understand what you mean by
that
you'll get that sort of those sort of
bursts of dopamine is not the joy juice
that the popular culture dopamine has to
do with salience and marking things
that's standing out important for
learning and arousing you for that
learning and so if you're giving that
survive right again that's because parts
of the brain are talking to each other
what's happening is a realization that
there's an opportunity for learning here
there's an opportunity for
transformation there's an opportunity to
inhabit and learn about in a very
participatory manner parts of your mind
and parts of your brain don't get caught
up in it that don't don't
definitely don't start framing it as
something you're seeking as the goal of
your practice that is mentis is there a
version of meditation that would be
appropriate for children so there's a
book meditating with children I'm very
cautious about this because we don't
know we don't have good research about
the relationship between meditation and
small children like children before the
age of formal operations like children
younger than let's say you know 11 or 12
so I'm hesitant about this getting them
to do the soft vigilance practice on
things getting them to simply count
their breaths and a little bit stablize
that's that's appropriate thing to do
you can check out the book meditating
for children it has some good
recommendations you also want a much
shorter term of practice but please
remember
don't push it very hard and don't try
and get into the depths of the practice
because we're very unclear from a
scientific perspective about how
meditation or mindfulness we know they
have important changes on the plasticity
of the brain it really it literally
changes the wiring of the brain and so
the way that interacts with the course
of
early development we don't know so me
just I would suggest keeping it very
very simple soft vigilance exercises
with the kids counting their breaths
keeping it short just something basic
like that mark again when Rudy we have
flow then we have flow at the next level
are these actually the same or if
they're a better term during routine
they're there they're pretty much the
same the letting it flow is within the
routing practice is designed to get you
into that state where you're starting to
track the expansiveness of your
experience and then you're refining it
when you're actually finding your flow
because you're not only doing the
expanse you're doing the enhancement of
all of the differences and putting them
into that sort of you know that
challenging dynamic opponent processing
all right so everyone thank you for
joining as always I want to thank
you.thank my techno mage Omar my beloved
son Jason please subscribe to the
channel to be notified of the next video
and an online channel you'll also find
lots of videos about you know meditation
contemplation mindfulness insight flow
mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness discussions about wisdom
enlightenment so if you to set this in a
broader practice which is ultimately
what you want to do because if you
remember the Buddhist tradition right
like meditation by concentration like
meditation right concentration are only
set within a whole comprehensive a life
comprehensive dynamical system of
practices and so learning how to situate
this into a broader philosophical way of
life where philosophy doesn't mean not
academic thing it means the cultivation
of wisdom and virtue is something you
should ultimately be considering please
invite others who might benefit by
sharing this series helped me to help as
many people as I can through this series
by sharing it as widely as you possibly
can
we're doing this every week days mondays
are Dharma day
Tuesdays and Fridays are sit days we do
it every weekday 9:30 est see you on
Monday for the next lesson take care of
everybody and remember that continuity
of practice is more important than
quantity of price